<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5">
	<spell>
		<name>Abi-Dalzim's Horrid Wilting (XGE)</name>
		<level>8</level>
		<school>N</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>150 feet</range>
		<components>V, S, M (a bit of sponge)</components>
		<duration>Instantaneous</duration>
		<classes>Sorcerer, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight)</classes>
		<text>You draw the moisture from every creature in a 30-foot cube centered on a point you choose within range. Each creature in that area must make a Constitution saving throw. Constructs and undead aren't affected, and plants and water elementals make this saving throw with disadvantage. A creature takes 12d8 necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
		<text>  Nonmagical plants in the area that aren't creatures, such as trees and shrubs, wither and die instantly.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
		<roll>12d8</roll>
	</spell>
	<spell>
		<name>Bones of the Earth (XGE)</name>
		<level>6</level>
		<school>T</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>120 feet</range>
		<components>V, S</components>
		<duration>Instantaneous</duration>
		<classes>Druid</classes>
		<text>You cause up to six pillars of stone to burst from places on the ground that you can see within range. Each pillar is a cylinder that has a diameter of 5 feet and a height of up to 30 feet. The ground where a pillar appears must be wide enough for its diameter, and you can target ground under a creature if that creature is Medium or smaller. Each pillar has AC 5 and 30 hit points. When reduced to 0 hit points, a pillar crumbles into rubble, which creates an area of difficult terrain with a 10-foot radius. The rubble lasts until cleared. Each 5-foot-diameter portion of the are requires at least 1 minute to clear by hand.</text>
		<text />
		<text>If a pillar is created under a creature, that creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or be lifted by the pillar. A creature can choose to fail the save.</text>
		<text />
		<text>If a pillar is prevented from reaching its full height because of a cieling or other obstacle, a creature on the pillar takes 6d6 bludgeoning damage and is restrained, pinched between the pillar and the obstacle. The restrained creature can use an action to make a Strength or Dexterity check (the creature's choice) against the spell's save DC. On a success, the creature is no longer restrained, and must either move off the pillar or fall off it.</text>
		<text />
		<text>At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, you can create two additional pillars for each slot level above 6th.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
		<roll>6d6</roll>
	</spell>
	<spell>
		<name>Catnap (XGE)</name>
		<level>3</level>
		<school>E</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>30 feet</range>
		<components>S, M (a pinch of sand)</components>
		<duration>10 minutes</duration>
		<classes>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight)</classes>
		<text>You make a calming gesture, and up to three willing creatures of your choice that you can see within range fall unconscious for the spell's duration. The spell ends on a target early if it takes damage or someone uses an action to shake or slap it awake. If a target remains unconscious for the full duration, that target gains the benefit of a short rest, and it can't be affected by this spell again until it finishes a slong rest.</text>
		<text />
		<text>At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 3rd.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
	</spell>
	<spell>
		<name>Cause Fear (XGE)</name>
		<level>1</level>
		<school>N</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>60 feet</range>
		<components>V</components>
		<duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
		<classes>Warlock, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight)</classes>
		<text>You awaken the sense of mortality in one creature you can see within range. A construct or an undead is ummune to this effect. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or become frightened of you until the spell ends. The frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
		<text />
		<text>At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 1st. The creature must be within 30 feet of each other when you target them.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
	</spell>
	<spell>
		<name>Chaos Bolt (XGE)</name>
		<level>1</level>
		<school>A</school>
		<ritual>YES</ritual>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>Touch</range>
		<components>V, S, M (25 gp worth of powdered silver, which the spell consumes)</components>
		<duration>Instantaneous</duration>
		<classes>Cleric, Paladin</classes>
		<text>You perform a special religious ceremony that is infused with magic. When you cast the spell, choose one of the following rites, the target of which must be within 10 feet of you throughout the casting.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Atonement: You touch one willing creature whose alignment has changed, and you make a DC 20 Wisdom (Insight) check. On a successful check, you restore the target to its original alignment.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Bless Water: You touch one vial of water and cause it to become holy water.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Coming of Age: You touch one humanoid who is a young adult. For the next 24 hours, whenver the target makes an ability check, it can roll a d4 and add the number rolled to the abiity check. A creature can benefit from this rite only once.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Dedication: You touch one humanoid who wishes to be dedicated to your god's service. For the next 24 hours, whenever the target makes a saving throw, it can roll a d4 and add the number rolled to the save. A creature can benefit from this rite only once.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Funeral Rite: You touch one corpse, and for the next 7 days, the target can't become undead by any means short of a wish spell.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Wedding: You touch adult humanoids willing to bonded together in marraige. For the next 7 days, each target gains a +2 bonus to AC while they are within 30 feet of each other. A creature can benefit from this rite again only if widowed.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
	</spell>
	<spell>
		<name>Chaos Bolt (XGE)</name>
		<level>1</level>
		<school>EV</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>120 feet</range>
		<components>V, S</components>
		<duration>Instantaneous</duration>
		<classes>Sorcerer</classes>
		<text>You hurl an undulating, warbling mass of chatoic energy at one creature in range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 2d8 + 1d6 damage. Choose on of the d8s. The number rolled on that die determines the attack's damage type, as shown below.</text>
		<text />
		<text>1-Acid.</text>
		<text />
		<text>2-Cold.</text>
		<text />
		<text>3-Fire.</text>
		<text />
		<text>4-Force.</text>
		<text />
		<text>5-Lightning.</text>
		<text />
		<text>6-Poison.</text>
		<text />
		<text>7-Psychic.</text>
		<text />
		<text>8-Thunder.</text>
		<text />
		<text>If you roll the same number on both d8s, the chaotic energy leaps from the target to a different creature of your choice within 30 feet. Make a new attack roll against the new target, and make a new damage roll, which could cause the chaotic energy to leap again.</text>
		<text />
		<text>  A creature can be targeted only once by each casting of this spell.</text>
		<text />
		<text>At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, each target takes 1d6 extra damage of the type rolled for each slot level above 1st.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
		<roll>d20+SPELL+PROF</roll>
		<roll>2d8+1d6</roll>
		<roll>1d6</roll>
	</spell>

	<spell>
		<name>Create Bonfire (XGE)</name>
		<level>0</level>
		<school>C</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>60 feet</range>
		<components>V, S</components>
		<duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
		<classes>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Fighter (Eldritch Knight)</classes>
		<text>You create a bonfire on ground that you can see within range. Until the spells ends, the bonfire fills a 5-foot cube. Any creature in the bonfire's space when you cast the spell must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d8 fire damage. A creature must also make the saving throw when it enters the bonfire's space for the first time on a turn or ends its turn there.</text>
		<text />
		<text>The bonfire ignites flammable objects in its area that aren't being worn or carried.</text>
		<text />
		<text>The spell's damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (2d8), 11th level (3d8), and 17th level (4d8).</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
		<roll>1d8</roll>
		<roll>2d8</roll>
		<roll>3d8</roll>
		<roll>4d8</roll>
	</spell>
	<spell>
		<name>Immolation (XGE)</name>
		<level>5</level>
		<school>EV</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>90 feet</range>
		<components>V</components>
		<duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
		<classes>Sorcerer, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight)</classes>
		<text>Flames wreathe one creature you can see within range. The target must make a Dexterity saving throw. It takes 8d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On a failed save, the target also burns for the spell's duration. The burning target sheds bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. At the end of each of its turns, the target repeats the saving throw. It takes 4d6 fire damage on a failed save, and the spell ends on a successful one. These magical flames can't be extinguished through nonmagical means.</text>
		<text />
		<text>If damage from this spell reduces a target to 0 hit points, the target is turned to ash.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
		<roll>8d6</roll>
		<roll>4d6</roll>
	</spell>
	<spell>
		<name>Transmute Rock (XGE)</name>
		<level>5</level>
		<school>T</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>120 feet</range>
		<components>V, S, M (clay and water)</components>
		<duration>Instantaneous</duration>
		<classes>Druid, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight)</classes>
		<text>You choose an area of stone or mud that you can see that fits within a 40-foot cube and that is within range, and choose one of the following effects.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Transmute Rock to Mud: Nonmagical rock of any sort in the area becomes an equal volume of thick and flowing mud that remains for the spell's duration.</text>
		<text />
		<text>If you cast the spell on an area of ground, it becomes muddy enough that creatures can sink into it. Each foot that a creature moves through the mud costs 4 feet of movement, and any creature on the ground when you cast the spell must make a Strength saving throw. A creature must also make this save the first time it enters the area on a turn or ends its turn there. On a failed save, a creature sinks into the mud and is restrained, though it can use an action to end the restrained condition on itself by pulling itself free of the mud.</text>
		<text />
		<text>If you cast the spell on a ceiling, the mud falls. Any creature under the mud when it falls must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 4d8 bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Transmute Mud to Rock: Nonmagical mud or quicksand in the area no more than 10 feet deep transforms into soft stone for the spell's duration. Any creature in the mud when it transforms must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a successful save, a creature is shunted safely to the surface to an unoccupied space. On a failed save, a creature becomes restrained by the rock. The restrained creature, or another creature within reach, can use an action to try to break free by succeeding on a DC 20 Strength check or by dealing damage to it. The rock has AC 15 and 25 hit points, and is immune to poison and psychic damage.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
		<roll>4d8</roll>
	</spell>
	<spell>
		<name>Watery Sphere (XGE)</name>
		<level>4</level>
		<school>C</school>
		<time>1 action</time>
		<range>90 feet</range>
		<components>V, S, M (a droplet of water)</components>
		<duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
		<classes>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight)</classes>
		<text>You conjure up a sphere of water with a 5-foot radius on a point you can see within range. The sphere can hover in the air, but no more than 10 feet off the ground. The sphere remains for the spell's duration.</text>
		<text />
		<text>Any creature in the sphere's space must make a Strength saving throw. On a successful save, a creature is ejected from that space to the nearest unoccupied space outside it. A Huge or larger creature succeeds on the saving throw automatically, and a Large or smaller creature can choose to fail it. On a failed save, a creature is restrained by the sphere and is engulfed by the water. At the end of each of its turns, a restrained target can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
		<text />
		<text>The sphere can restrain as many as four Medium or smaller creatures or one Large creature. If the sphere restrains a creature in excess of these numbers, a random creature that was already restrained by the sphere falls out of it and lands prone in a space within 5 feet of it.</text>
		<text />
		<text>As an action, you can move the sphere up to 30 feet in a straight line. If it moves over a pit, cliff, or other drop, it safely descends until it is hovering 10 feet over ground. Any creature restrained by the sphere moves with it. You can ram the sphere into creatures, forcing them to make the saving throw, but no more than once per turn.</text>
		<text />
		<text>When the spell ends, the sphere falls to the ground and extinguishes all normal flames within 30 feet of it. Any creature restrained by the sphere is knocked prone in the space where it falls. The water then vanishes.</text>
		<text />
		<text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
	</spell>
</compendium>